All right בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ד ayin
daled 74. We pick up at the bottom of ע"ג עמוד ב
ayin gimmel amud bet and we are in the middle of a
very important debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel and question how
to contextualize that debate about a woman who gets married on a
תנאי tnai on a condition and the condition isn't met.
But then after the קידושין kiddushin there is also a נישואין. nissuin.
How much the fact that they've been living together and having sex
together in a marital context means they're married even though the condition
wasn't met and how much the condition continues to frame it. רב
Rav says that the fact that they've had sex means they're married
now regardless. שמואל Shmuel says it's not. And the גמרא Gemara was
dealing with an approach of רבא Raba to try to say actually
in a normal case everybody would agree that it was on a
תנאי, tnai, the condition continues to frame the marriage, and he tried
to make the issue of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel a special
case of like a divorce and a remarriage and it was like
two women etc. But basically tried to argue that if it was
preceded by a תנאי tnai everybody would agree. And then the גמרא
Gemara also makes the distinction because it shows that there are opinions
of the תנאים Tannaim that when the first marriage was no good,
let's say it was less than a פרוטה pruta or it was
a קטן katan or something of that nature, it shows that actually
there are opinions on both sides of the equation whether the fact
that they now had sex together as a married couple makes them
married or not. And more importantly made a distinction between an explicit
stipulation and a קידושין kiddushin on error. A קידושין kiddushin on error
said, this is according to רבא's Raba approach, you can argue that
the fact that now they're living together as a married couple makes
them married.
But a קידושין kiddushin on תנאי, tnai, this is the position that
even רב Rav would agree, everybody would agree that that continues to
explicitly frame the ongoing marital relationship and therefore everybody would agree that
if the תנאי tnai is not met they are not married. So
that's where the גמרא Gemara is right now in terms of רבא's
Raba explanation of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, that in a תנאי
tnai everybody would agree. If there's a debate it would be in
that they're not married, that the תנאי tnai continues to frame it.
If there's a debate it would be in other cases.
Yes, is it major תנאי? tnai?
Yeah, we're not worried...
we're doing that only if it's תנאי, tnai, right?
Right, right. A תנאי tnai is a תנאי. tnai. No, no, no.
The major minor תנאי tnai is just to determine whether the תנאי
tnai was met. A תנאי tnai is a תנאי. tnai. I may
talk a little bit more about that later, but for now we're
not going to make any distinction. So now the גמרא Gemara continues
like this.
Okay איתיבי, Eitivei, five lines from the bottom starting with the asterisk.
מודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר, Modim chachamim le'Rabbi Eliezer, the חכמים Chachamim agree
with רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, there's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and חכמים Chachamim in a case where,
let's see what they agree to and then I'll tell you what
the case is. They agree with רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, this goes
back to יבמות's Yevamot case, שגירשה והחזירה כשהיא קטנה she'geirshah ve'hazira k'she'hi
ketana ביתומה בחיי האב bi'tuma be'chayei ha'av
והחזירה ve'hizra שחולצת ולא מתייבמת. she'choltzat ve'lo mityabemet. It's a little complicated.
A minor who was married off by her father and then נישואין,
nissuin, not just קידושין, kiddushin, then divorced. So now she is an
emancipated minor because after נישואין nissuin and then divorce she's a minor,
she's out of her father's control. And היא יתומה בחיי האב, hi
yatoma be'chayei ha'av, so that would mean she's like an orphan, she's
emancipated, she's no longer under her father's control. Okay, but she's not
an adult. So on the one hand her father can't marry her
off, on the other hand she can't marry herself off because she's
not an adult yet. והחזירה, Ve'hizira, and then she goes back to
her first husband. So in this case she's now back with her
first husband after she got divorced from her first husband after majority?
No, not after majority, so that's the point. It's only rabbinic marriage,
it's not a biblically binding marriage. Okay והחזירה. ve'hizira. Right, right,
so I guess the husband, the husband took her back. Okay, so
it's only a rabbinic marriage now שחולצת ולא מתייבמת. she'choltzat ve'lo mityabemet.
And now the guy dies, so in terms of the brother-in-law he
can only do חליצה chalitza not ייבום. yibum. He has to do
חליצה chalitza because it was a rabbinic marriage, he can't do ייבום
yibum because it is not a biblical marriage. Okay, and it's even
the worst of both cases because in a normal case if it
wasn't a biblical marriage and the guy would do ייבום yibum normally,
it wasn't really his brother's wife. But here it was his brother's
wife from the first marriage. Right? You got it? The first marriage
was biblically his brother's wife, the
second marriage didn't work. So this is a real איסור כרת issur
kares for the guy so let's do חליצה chalitza and avoid ייבום
yibum for the surviving brother.
מפני שגירושין גירושין גמורין ואין החזרתה החזרה גמורה Mi'pnei she'geirushin she'geirushin gemurin
ve'ein hazarata hazara gemura because the first divorce was a real divorce
and the remarriage was not a biblical
remarriage. במה דברים אמורים, Bi'meh devarim amurim, when is this true? שגירשה
כשהיא קטנה והחזירה כשהיא קטנה She'geirshah k'she'hi ketana ve'hizra k'she'hi ketana if
she's divorced as a minor and returned as a minor. אבל גירשה
כשהיא גדולה והחזירה כשהיא גדולה. Aval geirshah k'she'hi gedola ve'hizra k'she'hi gedola.
Or if she was divorced as an adult and returned as an
adult, or if she was divorced as a minor and returns as
an adult,
או שהחזירה כשהיא קטנה וגדלה אצלו, o she-he-chzirah kshe-hi ktanah ve-gadlah etzlo,
that's what's relevant for us, or even in the case where
she was returned as a minor, so it was only a rabbinic
marriage, but then she became an adult while they were married. So
the second time around, so this is the question, right? The second
marriage starts off as not being as only being at most rabbinic,
but they continue to be married, so then does that continued and
having sex, so is that create a biblical קידושין? kiddushin? So it
says in that case, wait, and then it says או חולצת או
מתייבמת o choletzet o mityabemet משום גט ומשום חליצה או ייבום mishum
get u-mishum chalitzah o yibum משום, mishum, okay, because that's fine, so
that basically is that idea that a קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktanah when
they continue to live together creates a קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin de-oraita. All
right, so and then the גמרא Gemara top of ע"א עמוד א',
Ayin-Alef Amud Alef, משום רבי אלעזר אמרו, mishum Rabi Elazar amru, it's
רבי אליעזר, Rabi Eliezer, in the name of רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
they said חולצת ולא מתייבמת. choletzet ve-lo mityabemet.
That no, even in that case you only do חליצה chalitzah and
not ייבום yibum because he's afraid that if you allow in this
case,
these last cases to do ייבום, yibum, it will lead to doing
ייבום yibum in the problematic case that we started with. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara means that רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer and חכמים
Chachamim debate about doing ייבום yibum in some of these cases about
a minor who got divorced and remarried and so on. Okay, but
they agree that
you cannot do ייבום yibum in the case where the second marriage
really is only rabbinic. The debate is when the second marriage became
דאורייתא. de-oraita. She was remarried as an adult or she was remarried
as a קטנה ktanah and she became an adult. There חכמים Chachamim
say, okay, now it's a good marriage דאורייתא, de-oraita, now you could
do ייבום, yibum, whereas רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says I'm not going
to allow ייבום yibum in this case either because I'm afraid that
it'll lead to the first case. Okay, but for what else is
relevant
is that the case of a קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktanah that becomes
binding דאורייתא de-oraita because they continue to live together. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says but you see that here's a case that everybody
would agree that continuing to have sex together, it seems like it
would become,
it would be קידושין. kiddushin. And you wanted to say that if
it starts by a תנאי, tnai, that everybody would agree that it
would not be that they would not be married. So the answer
is obviously what we said yesterday, the difference between קטנה ktanah and
תנאי. tnai. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. והכא בחדא
איתתא דמי, Ve-hacha be-chada iteta dami, it's all about one woman, it's
not like the case of the case about like two women that
the גמרא Gemara just discussed before or something similar to that. ופליגי,
U-pligi, and they debate, I mean, it's how רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
and חכמים Chachamim debate, what it only means is there's a position
that says that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and even רבי אליעזר
Rabi Eliezer really agrees that the continued living together constitutes means that
they're now married now that they are continuing to have sex as
an adult. So how could you say that if it starts with
a תנאי tnai everyone agrees that they're not married? What? So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, התם נמי רק מפלגי, hatam nami rak mipalgi,
מר סבר, mar savar, it's the same
point, it's funny, it's really the one between רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
and חכמים, Chachamim, but it means one side in the debate about
a קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktanah continuing to live together as an adult.
He says that, yes, we do find positions on both sides of
the debate. One holds that people know that the קידושי קטנה kiddushei
ktanah wasn't binding וגמר ובעל לשום קידושין ve-gamar ve-ba'al leshum kiddushin and
therefore the continued living together and having sex together constitutes an act
of
קידושין. kiddushin. ומר סבר אין אדם יודע שאין קידושי קטנה כלום, U-mar
savar ein adam yodeia she-ein kiddushei ktanah klum, that there's not an
awareness that the first one was not binding,
וכי קא בעל אדעתא דקידושין ראשונים קא בעל, ve-ki ka ba'al ada'ata
de-kiddushin rishonim ka ba'al, and continued sex is all defined by the
original context and it's not a new act of marriage and therefore
it remains not binding. But that is all fine and good when
it's the case by a קטנה. ktanah. But when it's a case
by a תנאי, tnai, says רבא, Rava, everybody would agree if you
explicitly state the תנאי, tnai, that תנאי tnai continues to frame the
continued married life, married relationship, and if the תנאי tnai is not
met, then even if they're living together and having sex, they are
not married. Again, this is very relevant as I said for these
discussions about using תנאי בקידושין tnai be-kiddushin as a possible solution to
the עגונה agunah problem. Here the גמרא, Gemara, at least according to
רבא, Rava, we're not done with the סוגיא, sugya, but at least
according to רבא, Rava, whatever questions there might be whether continued living
together constitutes קידושין, kiddushin, when you start with a תנאי, tnai, everybody,
רבא Rava and שמואל Shmuel would agree that that תנאי tnai continues
to frame it. By the way, let me tell you the other
scenario
in addition to this sorry תנאי בקידושין tnai be-kiddushin עגונה agunah solution,
is the case that רב משה Rav Moshe deals with a great
deal, which is a couple gets married conservative wedding and then they
don't get, they don't get a גט get and are the kids
ממזרים? mamzerim? And the question becomes,
and it's a, the reason I say conservative wedding is because very
often there you have, you had especially in the past, two כשר
עדים, kasher edim, two שומרי שבת, shomrei Shabbat, the rabbi and the
חזן, chazzan, no גט, get, what's the story? So if... And then
they don't get a גט get and all the kids ממזרים mamzerim
and the question becomes the reason I say conservative weddings because very
often there you have had in the past two כשר עדים, kosher
eidim two men שומר שבת, shomer Shabbos, the rabbi and the חזן,
chazzan, no גט, get, what's the story? So רב משה Rav Moshe
has this whole approach which where he basically says well because you're
associated with the conservative movement you're not בחזקת b'chezkas and therefore you're
פסול לעדות pasul l'eidus so even if the rabbi and חזן chazzan
are שומר שבת shomer Shabbos they're not כשר kosher עדים eidim, and
the woman was never married.
Okay and he's by himself on that. Exactly. Fine. Okay but fine.
So תנאי tnai also, okay, so it's sort of like the first
קידושין Kiddushin was פחות משווה פרוטה, pachas m'shaveh prutah, right? And then
they continue to live together. Does that
constitute a
separate קידושין Kiddushin or do we say no, ultimately it's framed by
the original act אדעתא דקידושין ראשונים בעל ada'ata d'Kiddushin rishonim ba'al and
therefore it remains and therefore it will be if the first thing
was no good then this also is no good, don't say that
the living together itself constitutes an act of קידושין. Kiddushin. So clearly
that's רב Rav משה's Moshe position that if the first act was
no good then everything that follows
is equally no good and that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara says.
The first case is the issue of תנאי tnai where according to
רבה Rabba everybody would agree, רבה Rabba would agree that if it
starts with a תנאי, tnai, the תנאי tnai continues to frame even
the marital sexual life afterwards and that cannot be a, and that
will not be a new act and if the תנאי tnai is
not met then they're not married. And if we find a debate,
it's where there is not a case of תנאי tnai but there's
a case for some reason the original marriage was not good. תנא
tana פחות משווה פרוטה, pachas m'shaveh prutah, the example I was giving
you, לא כשר עדים, lo kosher eidim, that's where
we'll find a debate
whether the fact that they're living together and having sex together as
husband and wife, are they considered married regardless or is it all
done based on the original act of קידושין? Kiddushin? Yes, first Michael
Mendlowitz.
Just a matter of clarification.
Hold on. I'm with you. Hold on.
Just to say when we're talking about living as or whatever having
sex together as husband and wife, you're saying that after the
marriage.
Well,
I wouldn't say that they would have to say that.
No, but here no, so I was saying you have asked and
this to some degree also has a question about how we פסקן,
pasken, how much you think that the person needs to have active
כוונה kavana to have קידושי ביאה. Kiddushei biah. So רש"י Rashi reads
this סוגיא sugya and it sounds like פשט pshat of the סוגיא
sugya is that way, that the person does have to have active
כוונה kavana to have קידושי ביאה Kiddushei biah and my point was,
but since you know that the first thing wasn't good, you actually
have כוונה kavana that this should be an act of קידושי ביאה
Kiddushei biah and so on. The alternative is to read it not
that way, but to just say and this is sort of where
I've been saying it because I think it's a little bit more
intuitive, is that the just the reality of living as man and
wife, of having sex together in a marital context without any particular
כוונה kavana itself creates קידושין. Kiddushin. That ביאה biah is different than
formal acts of קידושין. Kiddushin. And that's Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin. While
that is conceptually more attractive,
the downside of it is is that it leads to say and
that it pushes you more often to say that they're, that the
קידושין Kiddushin is binding because you're saying you don't really need כוונה,
kavana, you just need the reality of them living together as husband
and wife.
So you just need the sex.
Yeah, you need the sex, right.
So they still wouldn't be quote unquote officially married unless they had
sex.
Correct. Even if for example, let's say he went on a business
trip. Correct.
Right after she became his wife.
Absolutely. Absolutely. You need the sex, yes.
But in the case in which there is a תנאי tnai that's
uttered and then the sex follows, we're essentially saying that that frames
the action.
Well, it frames the action.
Yeah, and so right that informs the meaning. Exactly. Of that thing
or of that act. Exactly. Of the act. Yeah.
Absolutely. Very well said. Okay, those words speak very loudly. Okay, so
now moving on, so what's the next step? Okay, so that's רבה's
Rabba approach which says תנאי tnai is different than everything else and
תנאי tnai will always frame the ongoing marriage. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it's also taught, אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
amar Rabbi Yochanan המקדש על תנאי ובעל, hamkadesh al tnai u'ba'al, if
the קידושין Kiddushin was with a תנאי, tnai, on a condition, and
then they had sex, דברי הכל divrei hakol everybody would agree, presumably
I mean if you have the רבה Rabba as part of some
of the versions of the גרסא, girsa, but reading it that way,
רבה ושמואל Rabba v'Shmuel who seem to disagree, they if it was
a case of תנאי tnai they would agree that she does not
need a גט, get, the תנאי tnai continues to frame the marriage.
איתיביה, eiseivieh, the גמרא Gemara asked, רב אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav
Acha brei d'Rav Ika בר אחותו bar achasoh of רב אחא, Rav
Acha, בריה דרב איקא brei d'Rav Ika בר אחותו, bar achasoh, the
son of his, of his sister, of רב אחא, Rav Acha, wait,
he was the son of רב
איקא Rav Ika who was the בר אחותו, bar achasoh, sister's son
of, anyway, I'm not sure what the relationship was. He was the
son of רב איקא Rav Ika who was the son of the
sister. Yeah, that could work. Okay, wait what? Anyway, whatever, I don't
know, anyway, moving
on, okay, we'll figure that
out later. חליצה מוטעת כשרה. Chalitzah mutaat kshairah. Okay so it is
a anyway here's what he said if it is a חליצה chalitzah
in error then the it is still
כשר. kasher. איזהו חליצה מוטעת? Eizehu chalitzah mutaat? What is a חליצה
chalitzah in error?
אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish כל שאומרים לו kol she'omrim lo
חלוץ לה ובכך אתה כונסה. chalotz lah uv'kach atah kunsah. So they
tricked the guy into doing חליצה. chalitzah. Here's a guy who doesn't
know anything. He says oh well my sister-in-law I've always been interested
in her I want to do יבום yibbum and the rabbis realize
that no this is not a good idea for יבום. yibbum. They
say here's how you have to do יבום: yibbum: You gotta take
off the shoe spit out in front of you okay? And then
you spit out and then you say that you've done יבום. yibbum.
And they do that. So he says okay that works as long
as you did it even if it's an error even if it's
mistakenly done. So that would be good. So that was the first
explanation.
אמר יוחנן Amar Yochanan אם אמרו לו בכך
אתה כונסה
Im amru lo uv'kach
atah
kunsah you will bring her in you will be married to her.
Okay so do the חליצה chalitzah and that's the way you'll be
married. So אמר יוחנן Amar Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אני
שונה ani shoneh I teach בין שנתכוון הוא ולא נתכוונה היא bein
shenitkavein hu velo nitkavnah hi בין שנתכוונה היא ולא נתכוון הוא bein
shenitkavnah hi velo nitkavein hu whether it is the case that he
had intention to do
חליצה chalitzah and not
she or she had intention and not he חליצתה פסולה chalitzatah pesulah
it's invalid עד שיתכוונו שניהם ad sheyitkavnu shneihem until both of them
have the intention that it is an act of חליצה. chalitzah. ואת
אמרת חליצה כשרה? ve'at amart chalitzah ksheirah? And you say it's valid?
So it can't be that that type of an error is valid.
אלא אמר יוחנן Ela amar Yochanan here would be an example of
an error that would be valid: כל שאומרים לו חלוץ לה על
מנת שתיתן לך מאתיים זוז. kol she'omrim lo chalotz lah al menat
shetitein lach matayim zuz. They say do חליצה chalitzah and she'll pay
you 200 bits or you know ten thousand
dollars. So he has intention when he does חליצה chalitzah that it
should be an effective act of חליצה. chalitzah. He understands that חליצה
chalitzah severs the relationship but it's a trick because they're never planning
on paying him the money. Okay so there's two elements here one
is like he was tricked into it like he was given misinformation
you know maybe he wouldn't have wanted to do it otherwise. So
there's a question about like how much did he really want to
do it had he known the facts. But what's that's one element
and you could say like is it complete דעת da'at right if
you wouldn't have wanted to do it had you known all the
facts? But what the גמרא Gemara is sort of more focusing on
is that they say על מנת. al menat. על מנת al menat
is like an explicit תנאי. tnai. So you've explicitly made it conditional.
So how could it be that an explicit תנאי tnai in the
חליצה chalitzah is not doesn't work? Conditions should work. So let's see
so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אלמא Alma so you
see כל דעביד מעשה אחולי אחיל לתנאיה. kol de'avid ma'aseh acholei achil
letna'ei.
Since you did an act the act overrides I mean that's my
language the גמרא Gemara says by doing the act implicitly you waive
your condition.
הכא נמי Hacha nami exactly exactly the custom. הכא נמי Hacha nami
since he had sex אחולי אחיל לתנאיה. acholei achil letna'ei. You've
that overrides the you know that means an implicit waiving of your
condition. Now it's an interesting question what the גמרא Gemara is exactly
thinking. It might mean yes it does sound like we throw the
תנאי tnai out. But why don't we say that like by any
time? Right? Meaning every תנאי tnai should not be valid? Who right?
How about the fact that I make a תנאי tnai when I
give the ring? Why isn't that an act that waives my condition?
Like why is the sex the act that waives my condition and
not the giving of the ring? Why is חליצה chalitzah or let's
say I sell you a field on condition? How about the fact
I sell you my donkey? How about the fact I gave you
over my donkey? Why isn't that a waiving of the condition? The
whole point of the condition is to make conditional the act. So
it works. So the condition works when I give you my donkey
and the condition works when I give the woman the ring. Why
doesn't it work when I do the act of sex or I
do the act of חליצה? chalitzah? The גמרא Gemara seems to feel
and this will get to what the גמרא's Gemara like answer is
you know that the act of חליצה chalitzah the act of sex
are so much
involving me personally right? I mean it's not just simple like handing
over a ring handing over a donkey right? For a woman though.
Okay fine but I'm being degraded and I'm being you know spat
at and being yelled at or whatever you know shamed or whatever.
It's very much involving me personally and that degree of personal involvement
maybe says that I'm going through with this no matter what. Okay
that's at least how the גמרא Gemara wants to understand seems to
understand how חליצה chalitzah and ביאה biah are the same that way.
So you see once you do this serious type of an act
you're sort of saying like okay then you're like you're totally bought
in and you want it to be effective regardless. So if that's
true by חליצה chalitzah it should be true by ביאה. biah. And
therefore says the גמרא Gemara the exact opposite of what you're saying
that it should be that even with a תנאי tnai of where
sex it's always a good קידושין. kiddushin. So let's take a you
know it's always a binding marriage. So let's take a look. Right
so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר ליה בר דלפי Amar lei Bar Dalafai so So one of
the students of the ישיבה Yeshiva said, שפיר קאמרת, Shappir Ka'amarta, is
that a good question? מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look. כולהו תנאי
מהיכא גמרינן? Kulhu T'na'ei Mei Heicha Gamrinan?
Where do we learn out conditions from? That conditions can make acts,
legal acts like a connection be effective, make them, you know, binding
somebody from the, this men context. Yeah, well no, well, a student
in the ישיבה. Yeshiva. Okay, בר דלוא דחד יומא, Bar de Lava
d'Chad Yoma,
means like a one you know like a like a one day
old guy who in ישיבה. Yeshiva. All right, so says where do
we learn out that conditions make legal acts, you know, actually conditional,
that they have the effect of being like legally binding, those conditions
effective. מהיכא גמרינן? Mei Heicha Gamrinan? Where do we learn it out
from? מתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן, Mi-Tnai Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven, because
of בני גד ובני ראובן. Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven. Moshe said if
they pass over, then they'll inherit, you know, on the other side
of the Jordan, but if they don't go ahead then they'll inherit
with you in ארץ כנען. Eretz Canaan. So that's where we learn
the whole idea of conditions. So it says תנאי דאפשר לקיומי על
ידי שליח כהתם. Tnai de-Efshar L'kiyumei Al Yedei Shaliach k'Hasam.
If it's a condition that can be fulfilled through a שליח, Shaliach,
that doesn't actually mean that the condition could be fulfilled through the
שליח, Shaliach, it means if the act, if the act which is
conditional can be done not through the point himself but it can
actually be given over to another party to do, then הוי תנאיה
תנאה, Havei Tnai Tna'a,
then the condition is a condition. I will explain. Like over there
like בני גד. Bnei Gad. What
is that? דאפשר לקיומי על ידי שליח. D'efshar L'kiyumei Al Yedei Shaliach.
If the act cannot be done through a agent כהתם k'Hasam as
was the case over there, I mean there the act could be
done by an agent, but if it cannot be done that way,
לאו תנאה, Lau Tna'a, it would not be a condition. Now what
does that mean? Let's understand what it means by תנאי בני גד
ובני ראובן. Tnai Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven. Moshe was not the one
who gave them the land. יהושע Yehoshua was the end, the one
who in the end apportioned the land. So the act which is
dependent on the condition is something that the person who is, you
know, it doesn't have to be done by the person himself. Moshe
could give over the right and he actually did give over the
authority through somebody else to apportion the land. Similarly, so that's required
to make a תנאי Tnai binding. Similarly, if I go ahead and
I sell Michael this, my nice coffee cup here, right, and I
make it conditional on certain things, then that works because I could
empower David to sell my coffee cup to Michael. I can make
him my agent in selling the coffee cup. I don't have to
be personally present when I sell my objects. I can empower people
to sell things for me. Okay, similarly by קידושין. Kiddushin. I marry
a woman on a condition, right, as we know we learn מסכת
קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, right, and you take the story of אברהם Avraham
and his servant there, you can make people an agent to marry
a woman for you. Okay, and a woman can make somebody else
an agent to, to be married. So that's something that you can
have somebody else do for you, you can make a condition. חליצה,
Chalitzah, the argument is, is not something that I can have somebody
do חליצה Chalitzah for me, and I'll explain in a sec, which
we'll get to.
Okay, so therefore חליצה Chalitzah is therefore something says you know what?
By חליצה Chalitzah the condition isn't binding. It's not a principle that
an action override, it's a principle that חליצה Chalitzah is not something
that anybody else can do. And for things that nobody else can
do, conditions don't work. Now תוספות Tosafot says one minute. Okay,
what's the logic here? Like he says, we don't learn from בני
גד ובני ראובן Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven it has to be similar
to it in every arbitrary detail. Like why don't we just say,
well, it has to relate to the land of Israel? Why don't
we apply it by things that have to do with land? Okay,
or has to do with things that have to do with two
and a half שבטים? Shevatim? Okay, or things that are written in
the תורה? Torah? We don't say those things. There has to be
a logic of what we learn out. So what's the logic? So
if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תנאי דאפשר לקיומי על
ידי שליח, Tnai de-Efshar L'kiyumei Al Yedei Shaliach, he says ואם תאמר
מאי סברא יש כאן דלא גמרינן מהתם אלא אם נמשיך סברא דהא
אי גמרינן מהתם דלא הוי תנאי אלא בנתינת קרקע.
V'im Tomar Mai Svara Yesh Kan d'Lo Gamrinan mei-Hasam ela im Nimasheikh
Svara de-ha i Gamrinan mei-Hasam d'lo Hevi
Tnai ela b'Nesinas Karka.
There has to be some logic about why that should be the
only thing that relates to
תנאים. Tna'im. ויש לומר דהיינו טעמא דהואיל והמעשה כל כך בידו שיכול
לקיימו על ידי שליח. V'yesh Lomar de-Hainu Ta'ama de-Ho'il ve-ha-Ma'aseh kol kach
Biyado she-Yakhol l'Kayemo al Yedei Shaliach. I have so much power over
this act, let's say marrying a woman or selling my car, that
I can actually transfer that power to somebody else.
סברא הוא שתנאי כעין בידו לסמוך בו תנאי. Svara hu she-Tma k'ein
Biyado Lismokh bo Tna'ei. So I have power over the ability, right,
I am empowered to sell and to transfer, I can transfer that
power, so I can also control when that sale and the what
conditions that sale will be binding. I'm the one that shapes and
controls the act of the sale. Okay, אבל
חליצה שאין בידו לקיימו על ידי שליח. Aval Chalitzah she-Ein Biyado l'Kayemo
al Yedei Shaliach. But חליצה Chalitzah I can't give that power to
anybody else. לא בידו נמי לסמוך בו תנאי. Lo Biyado Nami Lismokh
bo Tna'ei. I don't have a condition to stick, make it conditional,
I don't have the ability to make it conditional. A way to
understand this is by חליצה Chalitzah we
say, we say that I am the Actually, חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza*'s funny
because it has the husband's words, the man's words, and the woman's
words, half of, okay, but let's say what, do we say the
man and the woman are the ones that are changing the status
through their act, and they're empowered to change a status through doing
an act, or do we say that the תורה *Torah* says no,
if you go through with this act, then your status will be
changed. You're not the ones changing it, the תורה *Torah* says do
this and in the word, the תורה *Torah* will, the law will
change your status, but not that you are changing the status by
doing this act. So who's empowered here? So the תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*
says is if you can transfer that to somebody else, that means
I'm empowered to sell this object and I can give you that
power. I'm empowered to marry a woman, I can give you that
power. I'm the one who's controlling and has the power, so I
can also say under what conditions it'll take effect. If I can't
give that power to you, then either I'm not the one who,
I do an action and then the status changes as a result,
but I am not somehow empowered and therefore I cannot make the
result conditional. So that's how תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* understand the idea of
אפשרי למיעבדי על ידי שליח shaliach *efshari l'meiavdi al yedei shaliach*. Which
by the way, like when I don't know if I mentioned this
so much when we did יבמות *Yevamot*, but there's a lot that
you see that יבום *Yibum* and חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza* that are true
about that. The fact that for example יבום *Yibum* says you needed
כוונה kavanah *kavanah* by חליצה chalitzah. *Chalitza*, but יבום *Yibum* didn't need
כוונה kavanah. *kavanah*. The very reality of having sex automatically creates the
result. Normally it needs me to intentionally do something because I'm the
one empowered and I'm the one who's actually shaping and doing it.
Or the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had the possibility that
חליצה chalitzah. *Chalitza* could be done by a קטן *katan*, right? And
there's the possibility that a קטן *katan* might be able to do
חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza*. Normally you need an adult to do חליצה chalitzah
*Chalitza*. How could a קטן *katan* do it? So that's if you
need the person to be, have דעת *da'at* and be the actor
and the agent. If they're not the actor and the agent and
they're not the one effecting it, it's just through their actions it
results, then you might even not need an adult and so on.
So therefore it says if you can't hand it over, that's an
indication that we're not empowered. You just do it and it happens
but you're not empowered and if you're not empowered you can't make
it conditional. And that's why conditions don't work by חליצה *Chalitza*.
Right, so just to take it for a point, is it like
the moment when someone becomes a citizen, like says the pledge of
allegiance or whatever, then the law of the land effects the status
and they become a citizen, like I don't have the power to
do that
but if I do the ritual and then the...
Yeah, maybe a way to think about another, I don't know if
I could go to a secular comparison, but a way to think
about it would be also like about מצוות *mitzvos*, right? Like I
can't transfer you the power to do a מצוה *mitzvah*. I do
the מצוה *mitzvah* and I get, but I don't know if that's
a helpful comparison.
I understood the words that you used to describe it, it just
touched something in my mind you were at, like what else...
Yeah, I don't know, I'd have to
think
about a secular parallel.
Yeah, but also in terms of the תנאי tenai *tnai*, it has
to be כמשפטי בני גד ובני ראובן *k'mishpatei Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven*
only one of the parties, right? It's not like both parties.
The power of the, well because the whole point is when they
get the land, they
themselves have to go, they individually need to go move home themselves,
but in the whole תנאי tenai *tnai*...
No, we're not saying do like that, the language is distorted, it's
confusing. You basically mean that תנאי tenai *tnai* can be fulfilled by
you or by somebody else. It means that the action which the
תנאי tenai *tnai* is making conditional can be done by somebody else.
You talk about the action about the, yeah, and then, right, the
transferring of the land, the act of חליצה *Chalitza*, the act of...
Right, but those could be separate, and say if I give him
$100, right?
Yeah, and then the תנאי tenai *tnai*'s on that matter. Yeah, exactly.
So the idea is that this person's role is so powerful that
he can do this even if he has a שליח *shaliach* do
it for him. We're saying that unless he can have a שליח
*shaliach* he can't do it.
Right. The fact that he is not able to assign an agent
means that he is fundamentally not the one that is empowered. He
is not seen as the one that effects this change. Okay, you
might do certain acts and the law will recognize as a result
changes of status, but if you cannot transfer that power to an
agent then you are not fundamentally empowered yourself. That's the idea. It's
more of a virtual, as opposed to a physical limitation. Like what
if you were sick and couldn't... Yeah, we don't mean physical limitation.
Although תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* gets, whatever, some questions come up about that.
But we mean in principle. In principle, if it's not a transferable
power, then we say that it's not a power at all. That
basically you're fundamentally not empowered. Yes, it's true, through certain acts this
woman will be free. You know, and this woman will no longer,
whatever, but it doesn't mean that you empowered, you free her. You
go through those actions and she becomes freed. You are not empowered.
And what about the case of שבועה *shvua*? Because you wouldn't...
Well, that was Michael's.
So let's bracket some other examples of where
you can't make a שליח *shaliach*. Well, ביאה biah. *bia* would be
one, which is now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to ask.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, so let's get... The argument was, the
argument was if תנאי tenai doesn't work by חליצה then a תנאי
tenai should not work by ביאה. biah? And how could you say
that תנאי tenai, works by ביאה? biah That was the argument. The
answer is no, that's not, that's a stupid argument. The תנאי tenai
doesn't work by חליצה cause nobody else could do the חליצה. So
the point is, okay, that's why it shouldn't work by ביאה biah
either. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
והא ביאה דשכיחא דלא משכחת לה ע"י שליח, veha biah deshekicha dela
meshakachat lah al yedei shaliach, right? Some other person couldn't do the
sex on your behalf. כי התם kee osom like there, דהוי תנאי,
dehovei tenai, it's not and the whole point is, the תנאי tenai
works for the continued act of sex, but it doesn't work for
חליצה. What's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם משום
דאיתקש הויות להדדי. hasom mishum de'iskesh havayos lehadadi.
That's because all of the forms of קידושין kiddushin are connected to
one another. והיתה, vehoysah, to become, is, you know, the word used
for קידושין. kiddushin. So since by what do you call it? Since
by כסף kesef and שטר shtar you can make a שליח and
you are empowered, even though the ביאה biah can only be done
by the man himself, nevertheless, it is considered that he is empowered
in that act and therefore can make that act conditional. Okay? So
that's what the גמרא Gemara answers. חליצה cannot be conditional because it
needs the man himself and therefore it is not able to be
made conditional. Sex, although it obviously requires man himself because it's part
of three types of acts of קידושין, kiddushin, conditions work by sex
as well. Alright, by the way, I do want to say, this
whole idea that is it about the physical action as opposed
to intentionally creating that status, gets back, is really at the center
to some degree of everything we've been talking about. Does the continued
married life itself constitute an act of קידושין? kiddushin? And Michael before
asked me, when I mentioned it yesterday, and if it does, do
you need specific intent, meaning מזומן ומוכן, mizuman ve'muchan, that this act
of sex will make a קידושין? kiddushin? To some degree that's the
same question. Is it just the physical reality of them having sex
and living together as husband and wife that itself makes them married?
Or is it an act that actually effects, you know, with intention,
is through this act I am going to effect this status change.
So that's a lot that has to do with this question of
how much is a תנאי tenai, relevant. If I am effecting the
status change through an act I can make it conditional. If the
act itself creates the reality, I can't make it conditional. So the
גמרא's Gemara still arguing that by חליצה I can't make it conditional,
but by ביאה biah you still can because even though ביאה is
much more me personally doing the act, nevertheless, it's similar to the
other acts of קידושין kiddushin and therefore can be made conditional. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues, let's take a look. אמר רב
יהודה אמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Ulla Amar
Rabbi Elazar: המקדש במלוה ובעל, hamikadesh bemilve uva,
if somebody starts to marry a woman with a loan, not giving
her money itself, but the woman, this woman borrowed a hundred dollars
from me and I said you know what, that hundred dollars that
you owe me, you'll be made with that. I didn't give her
real money, I forgave her a debt. I'm not going to get
into details about that, we can learn more about that one in
מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, but for now we'll understand that certain situations
like that don't work. But then afterwards we start living together and
have sex, או על תנאי ובעל, o al tenai uva, on a
condition and then sex follows, או בפחות משוה פרוטה ובעל, o befachus
mishaveh perutah uva, or less than a פרוטה perutah had sex, so
דכולי עלמא צריכה הימנו גט. dekulei alma tzrichah haymenu get. Everybody would
say that you need a גט. get. So this is saying the
exact opposite of what we've been saying. We've been saying that when
it's a תנאי tnai, everybody says you don't need a גט. get.
And the debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is in like
other cases. Cases where there wasn't a תנאי tnai or cases where
it's like two women, etc. Here we're saying the opposite, that everybody
says you do need a גט, get, whether it's a תנאי, tnai,
whether it's a case of a טעות, to-es, פחות משוה פרוטה, pachus
mishaveh perutah, whatever, everybody says that the act of continued living together
constitutes קידושין kiddushin and you need a גט. get. The exact opposite
of what we've been saying.
In all those cases where רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel are like
in משניות Mishnayot and קידושין kiddushin where he says you know, I
thought it was a tomato, it turns out to be a bagel.
Yeah, all those cases were just קידושין, kiddushin, but when they're followed
with sex, that's it. When they're followed with sex. So this is
of course very strict. There goes רב Rav משה's Moshe היתר heter
for ממזרות, mamzerus, there goes all these things. Continued living together and
so we go from one end of the stream that by a
תנאי tnai, everybody says you don't need a גט, get, there's a
debate about the non-תנאי tnai cases to the other extreme that says
whether it's תנאי, tnai whether it's טעות, to-es, everybody says you do
need a גט. get. Alright, now the question is where did רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel debate? What do you mean everybody? What about
these debates that we just talked about back here? What was that
about? So תוספות Tosafos. tries to work it out. תוספות Tosafos says
well maybe רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel were debating that they have
חופה chuppah but they didn't have sex. And what he's saying here
is once you've had sex, then everybody would agree that that's it,
that that creates קידושין kiddushin and you need a גט. get. So
let's take a look. Obviously some huge, huge halachic נפקא מינות nafa
minos based on which approach you take here. Okay. אמר רב יוסף
בר אבא אמר רב נחמן אמר רב אמי: Amar Rav Yosef bar
Abba amar Rav Nachman amar Rav Ami:
המקדש בפחות משווה פרוטה צריך הימנו גט. Hamkadesh bifochot mishaveh prutah tzarich
heimenu get. So he doesn't say all three, he only has the
case of less than
a פרוטה, prutah, then. But והא הכא, veha hacha, less than a
פרוטה, prutah, nobody makes mistakes. Everybody understood that the first act wasn't
קידושין kiddushin and therefore if the first act wasn't, he kept his
intent, presumably now you're having sex, you know the first thing didn't
count, so now you're intending for it to count. So now the
sex constitutes קידושין. kiddushin. But in the other cases, like the case
of with a loan or the case of by a תנאי, tnai
those cases they mistake and think that the first act is binding
and therefore you don't have to intend in the later sex for
that to be the act of קידושין. kiddushin. So this assumes the
reason sex would make them married is because it has intent to
make them married and therefore it would depend on whether you whether
you know enough to know that you need that intent, whether you
understood the problems of the first act, only if you understood it
you know enough to make this act of sex considered to be
קידושין.
kiddushin. Just on his position though that I was thinking about, thinking
about that since yesterday. So you made a mistake in thinking that
the first act was successful. But you don't have enough knowledge to
know that it wasn't.
So גמרא Gemara is saying you wake up the next day and
you do realize it wasn't effective and you have כוונה when you're
having sex to have this be a marriage.
I understand, and in all these
cases גמרא Gemara is consistent so
if you didn't he had this type of כוונה.
I agree with you.
Straight through גמרא's Gemara position.
Right. Okay. Now. גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר רב כהנא
משמיה דרב:
Amar
Rav
Kahana mishmeih deRav: המקדש על תנאי ובעל, Hamkadesh al tnai uva'al, somebody
that does קידושין kiddushin with a תנאי tnai, and then has sex,
going back to our case of תנאי, צריכה הימנו גט, tzricha heimenu
get, needs a גט. get.
So certainly it's not true like everybody agrees רבא Rava that that
doesn't need a גט, get, we're objecting רבא. Rava. Remember he started
with רבא Rava if there's a תנאי, everybody says you're good, no
need for a גט. get. Here we're saying either the opposite, everybody
says you need a גט, get, or at least רב Rav says
you need a גט get and we're ruling that way, we're ruling
לחומרא, l'chumra, that if it's a תנאי followed by sex, even if
שמואל Shmuel maybe disagrees with that case, רב Rav says you need
a גט get and we're ruling that you need a גט, get,
צריכה הימנו גט. tzricha heimenu get. Okay? And again, so there goes
using that for at least prima facie, there goes using that for
a for an עגונה agunah solution, right? If if that's what we're
concluding. וזה היה מעשה Vezeh hayah ma'aseh and this happened, it was
a תנאי and it was followed by sex, ולא היה כח בחכמים
להוציאה בלא גט, veloa hayah koach bachachamim lehotziah beloa get, and the
rabbis did not have the ability to say that you could walk
away without needing a גט. get. So that's also a pretty powerful
statement again, especially thinking about, you know, the whole עגונה agunah issues
because people say, you know, the rabbis could have you know, had
the power to do it if they want to do it and
they could always use הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin and so on, and
here the language is לא היה כח ביד חכמים. loa hayah koach
beyad chachamim. So here was an attempt to make a whole marriage
conditional and it's basically saying the rabbis' hands were tied. Even with
a marriage conditional, there was nothing that they could do. Because they
couldn't once there was sex they couldn't find a legal way to
decide with the
person... No, no, it's not they couldn't find a legal way. לאפוקי,
Le'afukei, but now the interesting thing is it doesn't mean that there
aren't opinions out there. They maybe felt that there were opinions they
couldn't rely on, but there actually are opinions. First of all we
have שמואל, Shmuel, right, who presumably was saying you wouldn't need a
גט. get. And also לאפוקי מהאי תנא, le'afukei mehai tanna, which is
rejecting the position of the following תנא, tanna, דתניא, detanya, דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי ישמעאל, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum
Rabbi Yishmael, because notice again it's שמואל Shmuel saying, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda in saying שמואל, Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel is the one that says
the תנאי does work, says in the name of רבי ישמעאל: Rabbi
Yishmael: והיא לא נתפשה, Vehia loa nitpasha, the woman who was raped,
let's say you know had sex with another man and it says
and she wasn't and a married woman and she wasn't raped. אסורה,
Asurah, so if she is, so this is the whole case by
the סוטה. sotah. So if she wasn't raped that she had sex
with another man, she's forbidden to her husband. הא נתפשה, Ha nitpasha,
the implication being that if she was raped, מותרת, mutteret, she's permitted
to her husband.
ויש לך אחרת, Veyeish lecha acheret, and there would be another woman,
שאף על פי שלא נתפשה, she'af al pi sheloa nitpasha, even though
she had sex with another man and she was not raped, מותרת,
mutteret, she would not be forbidden.
ואיזו זו, Ve'eizu zo, who would be this case? זו שקידושיה קידושי
טעות. Zo shekiddusheiha kiddushei taut. It's a
woman whose original marriage was in error, okay? There was some mistake
in the
way they married initially and she's been living
with this guy for last twenty years and then she went out
and she committed adultery, but it's not really adultery because the original
קידושין kiddushin was never binding even though she's been living with this
guy for twenty years,
שאפילו בנה מורכב על כתפה, she'afilu bnah murkav al ktefah, even if
now she's got a toddler here on her shoulders, so she's been
married, she has kids and the whole thing,
nevertheless ממאנת והולכת לה, mema'enet veholechet lah, she can say once it's
discovered that the original קידושין kiddushin was the cause, she can just
say that's it, I'm leaving, and she rejects her husband and walks
away. Okay? So here you have a very graphic, you know, picture
of the idea. that if the original קידושין kiddushin was an error,
and presumably error includes תנאי, you could discuss other errors as well,
which we'll get to in מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin or whatever, but
that everything afterwards is defined by the original act of קידושין kiddushin
and therefore no matter how many years they live together and have
kids and the whole thing, they're not married, she can walk away
at any time. Okay? So again we're aimed with very different voices.
You have the רצון ratzon to be a debate of רב Rav
and שמואל. Shmuel. You have one approach that says everyone agrees that
if it's בתנאי betnai she's not married and that's basically this last
as we have about the kid on the shoulders. And then you
have the other approach to say no, everyone agrees that she is
married if they had sex, or at least if not everyone agrees
that at least we פוסקין pasken that if they had sex they're
married even if it was בתנאי betnai and that was the story
about לא היה כח בידי חכמים. lo hayu koach biyedei chachamim. There's
a case where the חכמים chachamim felt they had no ability to
allow this woman to be free without a גט. get. So you
have very different, you know, approaches here and as I said, very,
very למעשה lema'aseh all of these issues.
You say some...
no, it's not a מחלוקת. machlokes. I mean there's some consensus at
least prima facie how we פוסקין pasken but then the question always
has to be about, you know, how we translate certain things.
Anyway, you could say the same thing as לא היה כח בידי
חכמים lo hayu koach biyedei chachamim in... ישמעאל Yishmael and שמואל Shmuel
and I'm sure I don't know where, I don't know where,
I'm not sure, I don't know where, you see, I can't even
get that. You know, you say the same thing nowadays, like why
do rabbis say they have no, you know, way of dealing with
עגונה agunah cases? There are opinions out there, you know, different rabbis
will feel that they have the, they feel that they can't rely
on those positions, other rabbis feel that they can rely on those
positions.
Right, they, they didn't feel that they could rely on those positions,
you
know. It's, you know, as more things change more they stay the
same. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. Okay, now, so that was the end
of that very intense and weighty סוגיא. sugya. Now we get to
some easier discussions relating to this same issue. Okay? Which is just
understanding whether the condition was met or not met. He says on
the condition that you don't have נדרים, nedarim, נמצא להם נדרים nimtza
lahem nedarim and she does have vows, so then she's not מקודשת,
mekudeshes, right? If they then went to have, if they've been living
together and having sex, that's what we've been talking about, but let's
even bracket they haven't been living together and having sex. It was
just קידושין kiddushin on the condition you don't have vows, she has
vows, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. Okay? Now we're going to talk about
some, some wrinkles. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, הלכה
אצל חכם והתירה, halcha etzel chacham ve'hitira,
מקודשת. mekudeshes. What's this? She had vows, she accepted the ring on
the condition she didn't have vows and she had made vows and
then after she got the ring, she went to a rabbi and
she did a התרת נדרים hataras nedarim and the rabbi got her
out of the vow. Okay? So then ah, then she was מקודשת.
mekudeshes. Now, the other case in the משנה Mishna was on the
condition that you don't have any blemishes, and she had blemishes that
he couldn't see or whatever, and but then afterwards she went אצל
רופא וריפאה etzel rofe vehirpasa to a doctor
and he cured her or healed whatever those blemishes were, you know,
אינה מקודשת, eina mekudeshes, then it doesn't matter, it doesn't work. So
the גמרא says what's the difference? And at the time of the
קידושין kiddushin the problem existed. Why does solving one thing later work
and solving the other thing later doesn't work? מה בין חכם לרופא?
Ma bein chacham lerofe? What's the difference between the sage and the
doctor? חכם עוקר את הנדר מעיקרו. Chacham oker et haneder mei'ikara. Because
the way התרת נדרים hataras nedarim works is if you go for
a התרת נדרים hataras nedarim then you say then the vow was
never binding at the outset. The basic way התרת נדרים hataras nedarim
works is that the rabbi says so, had you realized when you
took the vow that it would be this type of a circumstance,
you know, you'd be, you know, you'd be
in the following circumstance and how difficult this circumstance would be and
had you thought about that would you have taken the vow and
the person says no, no, no, if I actually thought about that
at the time I would never... Oh, okay, so then the vow
was never binding, you never really meant it. So
the effect of התרת נדרים hataras nedarim is is that it says
it
was never binding from the outset. So she goes to the, to
the חכם chacham and he
עוקר oker it retroactively,
then it turns out that a week ago when she took the
ring she never had the vow, right? Because now we look retroactively
and we see she never had that vow when she accepted the
ring. חכם עוקר את הנדר מעיקרו, Chacham oker et haneder mei'ikara, רופא
אינו מרפא אלא מכאן ולהבא. rofe eino mirapeh ela mikan ulhaba. Doctors
only cure her from this point on. They don't retroactively make it
that you didn't have the problem. Okay. והתניא... Veha tanya... Okay, so
that's a nice explanation, but let's keep on going. But we teach
in another ברייתא, braita, הלכה אצל חכם והתירה, halcha etzel chacham ve'hitira,
אצל רופא וריפאה, etzel rofe vehirpasa, if she goes ahead and gets
out of the vow and gets healed after she accepted the ring,
אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. It doesn't work in either case. It doesn't
even work in the case of the חכם. chacham. What's the difference?
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא רבי מאיר
הא רבי אלעזר. ha Rabbi Meir ha Rabbi Elazar. It's depending on
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. הא רבי מאיר
Ha Rabbi Meir דאמר אדם רוצה שיתבזה אשתו בבית דין, de'amar adam
rotzeh sheyitvazeh ishto be'veit din, because of this it works and she
is married is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says a person wants,
wants really means... you know, is okay with, but not ma... in
order to get a היתר נדרים heter nedarim might be something that
would be seen as unseemly. But רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir doesn’t consider
it unseemly, that doesn’t bother him. And
רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer אין אדם רוצה שתתבזה אשתו בבית
דין: so it would be unseemly. Now, how’s this relevant? So here
I am, I’m מקדש mekadesh a woman, I give her this ring
and I say on the condition that you don’t have נדרים. nedarim.
Now, if I think no wife of mine will ever go to,
she’ll go in front of a בית דין beis din to get
out for any reason, even to get out of her vows, and
it turns out that she has vows and she goes in front
of a בית דין beis din afterwards and gets out of it,
I could say I don’t care that you went and got it
annulled, I would never have, you know, that type of a scenario
is never one that I would have tolerated. So when I said
on the condition you don’t have vows, it included if you had
vows and you get out of it later, or whatever else, I
don't want to marry you under that condition because I would never
want you
to have to go to a בית דין beis din in order
to get out. So if I am object to my wife going
in front of a בית דין, beis din, then the condition that
you don't have vows
also excludes cases where you have vows and you’re going to get
out of it retroactively, because I don’t want that scenario to occur.
But if I don’t have a problem with my wife going to
a בית דין, beis din, then if I say on the condition
you don’t have vows, as long as even if you had vows,
as long as you could go to a בית דין beis din
and get out of it, that would be okay because then you
wouldn’t have vows and I have no problem with you doing that.
So whether or not it works, yes, in both cases retroactively you
didn't have vows, but in one case I'm okay with that and
therefore it's like my condition was satisfied, and in the other case
I’m not okay with you going into that בית דין, beis din,
so it’s like the condition was not satisfied.
But what about the יש באשה נדרנית? yesh b’isha nadranis?
So that’s true, meaning the question is it just the reality of
vows at this moment or is it about the habit of making
vows? If she knows... yes, תוספות discusses this as well and how
much we try to interpret exactly what was meant, but right now
we’re interpreting it more literally: were there vows at that time? And
then we're saying the fact that if there are vows that are
retroactively gone, that might still be considered vows if I don't see
that that is an option of getting them undone. Oh yeah, what?
Yeah, well we'll see, it's going to play into this
here.
Okay, so he's not in a bad position.
Right, exactly, exactly, exactly.
But but that's my point, meaning is it about her character as
a taker of vows or is it about the reality that she
has vows? And to some degree we try to get at what
his intent was. You know, it's not just the literal meaning here
too. If we went literally, we would say retroactively she didn't have
vows. But nevertheless, that's not a case you would have tolerated, her
going to a בית דין, beis din, so that doesn't change anything.
You could say that, you could say that, that's definitely something you
could say. Well, no, there's a debate between רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
and רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer what we normally assume about a man,
and we'll take a look at that.
Does she get the vows annulled after the...
after she takes the process of קידושין, kiddushin, yeah, after she takes
the ring, but it works retroactively. Okay, but if it turns out
that you were anyway... so we’ll take a look. So the גמרא
says like this. Okay, so the question about whether it works is
the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
whether we assume that a man is okay with his wife going
to a בית דין beis din to get out of her vows.
Okay. מאי
היא? Mai hi? Where is this debate? דתנן, D’tenan, we learned in
a משנה: Mishna: המגרש את אשתו משום נדר, ha’migaresh es ishto mishum
neder, if
a man divorces his wife because it turns out she has vows
and he said I don't want to be married to a woman
who has vows,
okay, או בגלל שם רע, o biglal shem ra, or because there’s
a rumor or suspicion that she’s committed adultery, לא יחזיר, lo yachzir,
he cannot remarry her. Now the reason he can’t remarry her in
those cases is because we don't want him then making trouble. If
basically here's what would happen: he would divorce her because there's a
rumor she committed adultery. She went out and she married another man,
she had kids, and then he said, oh my god, I just
found out you were telling the truth all along, you never committed
adultery, had I been aware of that I never would have divorced
you, the whole original divorce was an error and actually you're still
my wife and those kids are ממזרים mamzerim or whatever. Or he'll
say, oh my god, had I realized she had a vow I
divorce her, then she goes marries another man, then she goes to
a חכם chacham and gets out of the vow, and then I
say, oh my god, had I realized that you were going to
be able to get out of the vow by going to a
חכם chacham and do a היתר נדרים, heter nedarim, I never would
have divorced you, the whole divorce was an error and therefore, so
these are two cases where there is something that is, you know,
that can easily be be like be like reversed, the impression of
it. Like the impression there clearly was a vow but it could
retroactively be undone. There's a rumor but it could be determined that
the rumor was false. So therefore, so that I should not be
able to make trouble like that, the rabbis are saying I cannot
remarry her regardless, there's no way you'll be allowed to remarry her.
What's the effect of saying that? So here's the debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות. תוספות says if I can't remarry her, I'm not
going to I have no incentive to make trouble because the reason
I would be a troublemaker is because I want to get her
back. If you're not going to let me get her back, I
wouldn't bother. I mean that's a little generous of human nature. Okay,
I have plenty of reasons that I can't get her back, just
because I have a lot of other reasons that I don't like
the guy, I'm jealous, I'm this or that, doesn't matter if I'm
going to take get her back. So רש"י Rashi says, if I
know that I can't remarry her, I can't say the divorce was
an error because what the rabbis say is, you should know no
matter what happens later, you'll never be able to remarry her. So
if you're divorcing her, it means you're divorcing her unconditionally. Okay, and
therefore there's no claim that oh had I known it was whatever,
because if you already told me it had to be unconditional, it
would be irreversible, then then clearly I have the גמירות דעת gemirut
da'at to divorce her. Okay, so that's why I cannot take her
back, לא יחזיר. lo yachazir.
Now it goes on to say, okay, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
Omer, כל נדר שידעו בו רבים לא יחזיר, kol neder sheyad'u vo
rabbim lo yachazir, לא ידעו בו רבים יחזיר. lo yad'u vo rabbim
yachazir.
If it was a public נדר neder I cannot take her back,
if it was not I can. What's the difference? So רש"י Rashi
says that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not so much afraid that
I'm going to be מוציא לעז, motzi la'az, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is more afraid that the reason that I cannot take her back
is actually the opposite, it's actually a type of a fine against
the women, that because we don't want, you know, we want to
stop women from maybe getting into situations of that lead to suspicions
that they've committed adultery or to stop women from, like, you know,
making vows, you know, we're going to have this fine that if
the divorce is a result that's it it's going to be like
absolute and they're not going to ever be able to be remarried,
very harsh way of looking at it, because of my suspicions about
my wife, and yet he sees it as a fine against the
women. And therefore he says by vows case, if she's only in
private vows, what she did is not so bad and there's no
reason to be so strict and say you can't remarry her. But
if she is like even no she goes ahead and makes vows
in public, that's the behavior that we want to censure, that we
want to limit. So therefore we're going to be stricter about it
and say if a woman is doing that and the husband divorces
her, don't remarry. Okay, so that's his approach, that's not as relevant
for us, and so we'll just bracket that. And it says like
this, רבי מאיר אומר כל נדר שצריך חקירת חכם לא יחזיר, Rabbi
Meir omer kol neder shetzarich chakirat chacham lo yachazir, ושאינו צריך
חקירת חכם יחזיר. veshe'eino tzarich chakirat chacham yachazir. If a vow requires
going to a חכם chacham in order to get it annulled, then
he says, then you cannot take her back because that's exactly the
case. She'll go to a חכם, chacham, she'll get it annulled, and
then she'll come back and then I'll say, oh had I known
I never would have wanted to divorce you. So if it's a
case that she needs to go to a חכם chacham to get
it annulled, then it's something that I cannot take her back. If
it does not need to go to a חכם, chacham, what vow
does not need to go to a חכם? chacham? So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says it's going to be the vow that I the
husband can annul myself. You don't need to go to חכם, chacham,
I can annul myself. So if my wife makes a vow that
I have the power to annul and I go ahead and I
divorce her anyway,
even that, yes, and I go ahead and I divorce her anyway,
so to speak, the point is, I can't say had I known
you could have gotten out of the vow I wouldn't have divorced
you, because I could have done it myself, and I nevertheless divorced
her. Okay, so if I could do it myself and I divorce
her, then I can take her back because I will never be
able to claim had I known this I never would have divorced
you, because I didn't no no I can, the reason I can't
take it back is because I would then get married and then
I'll say, oh had I known this I never would have divorced
you, I can't say had I known I oh I did know
when I divorced her so the divorce is obviously a binding divorce
regardless. So that's why you can annul it yourself. Now what's relevant
for us is that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that the fact
that she could go to a
חכם, chacham, oh had I known I wouldn't have divorced you, meant
that it is feasible that she would go to a חכם. chacham.
I could imagine my wife could go to a חכם, chacham, right?
And therefore I could say had I known you had that ability
that would have then that would have been something I would have
wanted you to do, I never would have wanted to divorce you.
So that's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he says if it's a case
where I couldn't have done it myself and she needed to go
to a חכם, chacham, then I can't take her back because then
I might create trouble saying had I known you would have done
that or could have done that or whatever I wouldn't have divorced
you. All right, but that means that it's feasible for her to
go to a חכם. chacham. Let's just finish. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer,
אומר or אמר רבי אליעזר amar Rabbi Eliezer with parentheses, לא אסרו
זה אלא מפני שאינו זה. lo asru zeh ela mipnei she'eino zeh.
They do not forbid the case of when she needed a חכם
chacham except for the case of not needing a חכם. chacham. Meaning
he says the opposite. He says if it's something that only could
be got out of by going to a sage to undo it,
then that we're not concerned about. Why are we not concerned about
it? Something that she needed to go to a sage to undo?
I could say had I known I never would have divorced you.
Because this is what the גמרא means, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
because I would never have wanted any wife of mine to go
to a חכם. chacham. Okay, so I cannot come and say, because
it's a bit of a ביזיון bizayon to go to a sage.
So I can't come and say after she remarried, oh my god
had I known you would have gone to a חכם chacham I
never would have divorced you. What's that mean? You
never you never would you never would... So what רבא *Rava* says
is the case of when she needs a חכם *Chacham* is not
itself the problem. The problem is when she doesn't need a חכם
*Chacham*. When I divorced her and I could have been מפר *mefer*
it and then I could say, had I known, what do you
mean had I known? Well I didn't realize I could be מפר
*mefer*. I never learned that פרשה *parsha* in the תורה *Torah*. Nobody
ever told me I could be מפר *mefer*. Had I known I
could have been מפר *mefer* I wouldn't have divorced you. So רבי
אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* says the exact opposite of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*.
You could say had I known I could have been מפר *mefer*
I wouldn't have divorced you, but you can't legitimately say had I
known you could have gone to a חכם *Chacham* I wouldn't have
divorced you because we assume that men don't want their wives to
go to a חכם *Chacham*, okay? So רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* says
ולא זו אף זו *v'lo zu af zu*, you're right, you can't
remarry her even when she needs a חכם *Chacham*, but that's only
a גזירה *gezeira*. They only forbade the remarrying in the case of
needing a חכם *Chacham* אטו בשאינו צריך *atu besheino tzarich* because of
the case of not needing a חכם *Chacham*. The case of saying
I didn't realize I could be מפר *mefer* the נדר *neder*. And
because of that case we're saying I won't even be allowed to
remarry her in a case where I couldn't be מפר *mefer* but
she needs a חכם *Chacham*. Okay, so the bottom line is, I
mean that part was a little confusing, but bottom line is that
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says it is legitimate to say you know
I that the husband could have said that like had I known
you would have gone to a חכם *Chacham* that would have changed
things, which shows that according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* it would
be reasonable for a wife to go to a חכם *Chacham* to
get התרת נדרים *hatarat nedarim*. And רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* says even
had he known she could have gone to a חכם *Chacham* it
wouldn't have changed things because you never would have wanted your wife
to go to a חכם *Chacham*. So how does that translate back
here is when the guy says on condition you don't have a
נדר *neder*, and she has a נדר *neder* but she can get
out of it by going to a חכם *Chacham*, according to רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that's like not having the נדר *neder* because that's
a reasonable thing to do, go to a חכם *Chacham* get out
of it or whatever and then I'm okay with that. And according
to רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* it still is like having a נדר
*neder* because I never want my wife to go and if you
need to go or whatever then that's not a condition that I
want to marry you with. I want to marry you on condition
that you have no נדר *neder* right now so that you'll never
be required to go to a חכם *Chacham*. Okay? So a little
confusing but I hope you got that and we will end with
that for now. All right.
גמרא *Gemara* part?
Yeah, almost שבת *Shabbos* time. Apparently she's accepting the גט *get*.